<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kurcz Valentin</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kurcz Valentin</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 17:53:55 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Program visszafejtés - No. 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/program-visszafejt%C3%A9s-no.-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 17:53:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/program-visszafejt%C3%A9s-no.-1/</guid>
      <description>Bevezető a reverse engineering világába, ahol kezdő szintű program visszafejtős feladatokat oldok meg, bemutatom a technikákat és az alapokat. Csak annyit tudok mondani hogy: &amp;ldquo;Ki itt belépsz, hagyj fel minden reménnyel.&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>::Myprojects::</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2024 20:48:10 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/</guid>
      <description>Here you can find all my noteworthy works and pet projects that I have done over the years. These were either done self-taught or within my studies in my free time.&#xA;Fractal tree and other small programming tasks circa 2022 I started programming to get familiar with different languages and to fulfill my creative desires. One result of this period is this fractal tree generator, which was very inefficient, but at least I learned about the usefulness of rotation matrices early on :)).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The consequences of the Information Revolution and the Internet</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/the-consequences-of-the-information-revolution-and-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 17:47:21 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/the-consequences-of-the-information-revolution-and-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>The internet is one of the sharpest double-edged swords in our world. Its positive impact on commerce and, consequently, the economy is unquestionable. However, it remains a question of what price society and people have paid for this.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locality-Aware programming</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/locality-aware-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 09:45:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024/07/locality-aware-programming/</guid>
      <description>It is crucial how we traverse a matrix, whether column-wise, row-wise, or randomly. This article explores how to leverage our knowledge about computers for the benefit of our programs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>::Aboutme::</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 13:45:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m Valentin Kurcz, a 19 years old , hungarian, carbon-based computer engineer student at the Budapest University of Technology and Economics (BME), and I&amp;rsquo;m glad to meet you. I love repairing and tinkering old stuff, creating new things, hiking, baking pizza, also I love westend movies, and sliced bread. Oh and my toothbrush is purple. You can find my projects and works on this website, but also my takes and thoughts on many topics, to which you can always leave a comment or two, if you want to express your opinion.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
